<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Remedies for diseases in horses Approued and allowed by diuers very auncient learned mareschalles.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1576</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 31 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 14 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10597</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20870</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S102937</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838697</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838697</idno>
            <idno type="VID">3085</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10597)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3085)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1151:09)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Remedies for diseases in horses Approued and allowed by diuers very auncient learned mareschalles.</title>
                  <author>Malby, Nicholas, Sir, 1530?-1584, attributed name. aut</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[24] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>In Paules churchyarde, at the signe of the Lucrece, by Tho. Purfoote,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1576.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Often wrongly attributed to Sir Nicholas Malby.</note>
                  <note>Usually bound with an edition of: Malby, Sir Nicholas. A plaine and easie way to remedie a horse that is foundered in his feete.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-C⁴.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; folded woodcut of horse lacking.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Horses --  Diseases --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:3085:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3085:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>¶Remedies for di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſes in Horſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Approued and allowed by diuers</hi> very auncient learned Mareſchalles.</p>
            <figure/>
            <p>¶<hi>Imprinted at London in</hi> Paules Churchyarde, at the ſigne of the Lucrece, <hi>by Tho. Purfoote.</hi> 1576.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:3085:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3085:2"/>
            <head>To the right Honorable, and his ſinguler good Lord, the Lord <hi>Robert Dudley,</hi> knight of the honorable order of the Garter, Maiſtie of the Worſt, and one of the Queenes maieſties moſt honorable priuie Counſayle.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>YOur large renowme and wel deſerued prayſe</l>
               <l>(Moſt noble Lord) in prudent ſhal profounde,</l>
               <l>In marcial feates, whoſe like in theſe our dayes</l>
               <l>By iuſt accompt ſcarſe any where is founde,</l>
               <l>Ioyned with th'zeale borne to your countrey ground,</l>
               <l>Hath prickt me forth, and much hath moued mee,</l>
               <l>My poore good wil to ſhewe in ſome degree.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And for becauſe your Lordſhips office is</l>
               <l>Moſt worthely aſſigned by our Queene,</l>
               <l>To viewe and ſee that nothing be amiſſe</l>
               <l>About her horſe and ſtable as I ween<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</l>
               <l>But that the ſame in time may be foreſeene,</l>
               <l>Vnto your Honour humbly I preſent</l>
               <l>This Treatiſe ſmal, to further that intent:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Beſeeching you to take this in good part,</l>
               <l>Euen as the ſame with ſingle minde is ment:</l>
               <l>Way not the gift, regarde the geuers hart,</l>
               <l>My trauayle ſhal happely be ſpent,</l>
               <l>And you alſo reſemble verament</l>
               <l>That worthy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing, that tooke with thankful minde</l>
               <l>A draught of water of a ſimple hinde.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Although this volume ſmal do ſeeme in ſight,</l>
               <l>No little foulte yet therein ſhal you finde,</l>
               <l>A Larke in worth doth farre ſurmomit a Kite:</l>
               <l>A grayne of golde by doome of eche mans minde,</l>
               <l>A pounde of leade to paſſe is aye aſſignde:</l>
               <l>The Diademe in value farre exceedes</l>
               <l>Great maſſy rockes: fine flowers large ſtinking weedes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:3085:3"/>
               <l>This little booke ſhal teache you ſoone to knowe</l>
               <l>Th'original cauſe of eche infirmitie,</l>
               <l>That in an horſe by any meanes may growe,</l>
               <l>The name, the place of euery malady,</l>
               <l>And howe you ſhal the cure thereto apply:</l>
               <l>So as you may by remedies founde,</l>
               <l>Preſerue his health, and keepe him ſafe and ſounds.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For though you haue a comely Courſer great,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Pegaſus</hi> vnto his ſyre he haue,</l>
               <l>Though paſſing trim the troden wayes he beate,</l>
               <l>With loftie looke that trotteth fine and braue,</l>
               <l>With raine as round as hare can wiſhe or craue</l>
               <l>As trimly treade, can yarke aboue the grounde,</l>
               <l>And ſeemely ſaulte and turne both light and rounde.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Although he can the Galliarde gallope to,</l>
               <l>Paſſe the Carrier, the Cornettie can daunce,</l>
               <l>Can fetche the Capriol, and other trickes can do,</l>
               <l>As braue and fine as any hence to Fraunce:</l>
               <l>What doth auayle theſe vertues to aduaunce,</l>
               <l>By diligence thus brought to perfect frame,</l>
               <l>If afterwarde he fal diſeaſde or lame?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Which to preuent this little Treatiſe vſe,</l>
               <l>That ſhal (I truſt) in daunger him defende.</l>
               <l>As time doth ſerue vouchſafe it to peruſe:</l>
               <l>And ſo moſt humbly here I doo intende</l>
               <l>My leaue to take, beſeeching in the ende</l>
               <l>Almightie Ioue, whom you both loue and ſerue,</l>
               <l>Your Lordſhip long in honour to preſerue.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your L. moſt humble <hi>T. Purfoote.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:3085:3"/>
            <head>Remedies for diſeaſes in Horſes.</head>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <head>1 Stuffynge or colde in the head.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">K</seg>Epe his head and bodie warme, lette his drincke be warme water mingled with wheate meale, and fenell ſeede bruiſed. Blow vp into his noſethril<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les by ſome ſmall cane or reede, the poulder of <hi>Ellebor,</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly called Sneeſyng poul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and Peper myxt together. Take alſo a pinte of good Malmeſey, the whites and yolkes of fyue newe layed egges, one head of Garlyke bruiſed ſmall, Peper, Cynamone, and Nutmigges beaten into fine poulder, a preaty quantitie of ſweete but<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter: mingle them all together, and geue it him war<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me to drinke three dayes together: and lette him not drinke in three howres after euery tyme he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiueth it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <head>2 The Poze.</head>
               <p>TAke Orpiment and Sulphur, burne them on the coales, and by ſome preatie tonnell cauſe the horſe to receyue the fume thereof into his noſe. Or blowe vp into his headde the poulder of <hi>Ellebor</hi> and Peper, as is aforeſayde.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <head>2 The Poze.</head>
               <p>TAke y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> oyle of Bayes and Butter mingled to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and ſquyrt it warme into is noſe thril<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>les,
<pb facs="tcp:3085:4"/>
and holde his headde high, that it maye the better runne into his head: keepe his head and bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die warme, and let him drinke nothyng but warme water, mixte with fenell ſeede, and wheate meale as is aforeſayde.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <head>3 Dymneſſe of ſight.</head>
               <p>TAke a ſharpe hotte yron, and make ther with an hole vnder the dim eye, diſtante the ſpace of one ynche: and thruſte the ſayde yron vnto the bone, that the humour may iſſue out.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <head>3 The watry eye.</head>
               <p>LEt him bludde on the veynes vnder the eye, then waſhe the eye twyſe or thriſe in the daie, with good cleere whyte wyne, after that blo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame eye the poulder of Tartar, <hi>Salgem,</hi> and Cuttle bone of lyke quantitee. Or, Take the yolke of an egge roſted harde, myxe therewith the poulder of Cummyn, and bynde them hotte to the eye and lette them ſo reſt a nyght or more.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <head>3 The Hawe.</head>
               <p>CVte out the Hawe, and annoynt the eye .vi. dayes together with Salade oyle, the marro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we of ſheepes ſhankes, and ſalte mixte toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <head>3 The Webbe.</head>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:3085:4"/>ANnoynte the eye with the marrowe of Goa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes ſhankes, or Deere ſhankes, and Roſe wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter mixt together. Or ſquirte into the eye the iuyce of the bearies or leaues of ground yuie, or of other yuie, mingled and ſtrayned with good and cleere whyte wyne. Or, Blowe into the eye, the poulder of blacke flynte but ſee that the ſame poulder be exceedynge fyne, and ſo fyne as is poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible to be made.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <head>3 Blude ſhotten:</head>
               <p>TAke one dramme of Synoper, one dramme of pure honie, and ſo much of wheate flower, myngle them with fayre water, ſo that they maye be lyquide and thynne, then ſeath them with a veraye ſofte fyer, vntyll that they be thycke, like vnto an oynctement, and there with annoynte the eye. The whyte of an egge layde vpon the eye: or the iuyce of Chelydyn dropped into the eye: or the croppes of briers ſodden in good whyte wine, and the eye waſhed therwith be verie good,</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="part">
               <head>4 The Lampas.</head>
               <p>TAke an yronne crooked lyke vnto a bugle, heat it in the fyre, and let him bludde on the ſore parte of the roofe of the mouth, where it is moſte ſwollen, rubbe the place after that, with ſalte and ſharpe vyneger.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:3085:5"/>
               <head>4 The ſwellyng of the pallate.</head>
               <p>PRicke the roofe of the mouth with an hotte yron, that the humoure maie iſſue out abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly: then annoynte the place withe hony and onyons boiled together: or waſhe it with vy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neger and ſalte as is aforeſayde.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="part">
               <head>4 The Barbes.</head>
               <p>CVt out the pappes or bigges cleane by the roo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes, with ſome ſharpe inſtrume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te: after that, waſhe the place with ſalte, Tartar, and ſhar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe vyneger, myxte together.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="part">
               <head>4 The Tongue wounded.</head>
               <p>IF the tongue be wounded, either with the bit<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te or by any other hap. Take Engliſhe hony, ſalte larde of lyke quantitie, vnſleked lyme a lyttle quantitie, and a lyttle quantitie of the poul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der of Peper, boyle them on a ſofte fyre, and ſtirre them well together, vntil that they be thicke like vnto an oynctment: then waſhe the wound with whyte wine warmed: after that annoynt the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unde with the ſayde oynctment twyſe in the daye. Put no bytte in his mouth vntyll he be perfectly whole.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="part">
               <head>5 The Vynes.</head>
               <p>Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they be full ryppe, ſlytte the ſkinne, and take
<pb facs="tcp:3085:5"/>
them out cleane by the rootes: And to heale them, ſtrowe on the place, the poulder of hony and vnſle<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ked lyme burnte together.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="part">
               <head>6 The Strangles.</head>
               <p>VSe the foreſaide practiſe as before for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes: if the wound bleede ouer much, take ſharpe vyneger and ſalt, and diepe therin the flockes of wollen clothe, and putte them into the wounde, and lette them ſo reſte three dayes: than waſhe the wounde with whyte wyne war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med: after that annoynte it with Oyle and Tarre myxed together.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="part">
               <head>7 Starkenes of the necke.</head>
               <p>THruſte through the fleaſhe of the necke with a ſharpe hotte yron, in fyue ſeuerall places, eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one diſtant from the other three inches: (but be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ware of hurtynge the ſynewes) then rowell the fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſayde places, eyther with horſe heare flaxe, or hempe .xv. dayes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="part">
               <head>8 Wrounge on the wethers.</head>
               <p>IF the place be muche ſwolle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and feſtured, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> perce it with a ſharpe hot yron in many par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes on both ſydes of the necke, and put into the ſame tentes of lynnen cloth dieped in warme Salade oyle. And to heale it ſtrowe thereon the poulder of honye and lyme burnte together.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="part">
               <head>9 Swollen backe.</head>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:3085:6"/>CLippe of the heare on the ſwollen, place then take a good handful of the blades of leekes beate them in a morter together with Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes greaſe, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> heate them in ſome veſſell, and lay them hotte on the ſwellynge, and clappe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſadle, but ryde him not vntyll he be perfy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tely whole.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="part">
               <head>10 Naue galle.</head>
               <p>IF the ſkynne be broken, waſhe the place fyrſte with warme vyneger, then ſtrowe thereon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> poulder of hony and vnſleked lyme burnte together.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="part">
               <head>11 Spurre galle.</head>
               <p>WAſhe the place with water and ſalte, or with warme vyneger, and bynde on the place, the croppes or leaues of nettles ſtamped.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="part">
               <head>12 Hyde bounde.</head>
               <p>FIrſt bath his bodie with warm water, wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>in baye leaues be ſodden, then annoynt him all ouer with oyle of Rue or Camomill, and rubbe his ſkinne well, that the foreſaid oyle maie ſynke in, and that his ſkynne maye be ſouple and lymbre: after that geue him this drinke. Take Carretts. gumme <hi>Tracacanth,</hi> Rue, wylde Mynte, of euery of them one ounce and an halfe, Perſely, <hi>Sec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ula Campana,</hi> wormwood, of euery of them lyke quantitie, beate them, and ſeath them in water, and geue it him to drinke warme with ſome Mal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>meſey.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:3085:6"/>
               <head>13 The Spauan.</head>
               <p>CLyppe of the heare: the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> take Muſtarde ſeede, the great Mallowe roote, Oxe dunge, ſo mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che as thou ſhalte thinke neceſſarie, and ſo muche ſtrong vyneger as ſhall ſuffice, myngle the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and beate them well together, and make thereof a ſofte plaiſter or oynctement lay it vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, chaunge it eueninge and mornynge, and byn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de it in ſuche ſorte to the Soraunce with ſome peece of clothe, that it maye not fall of, or be remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued: and when the Spauen is cleane gone, laye vppon the place a plaiſter of Pitche, and take it not of, vntyll it falleth of by it ſelfe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="part">
               <head>14 The Splent.</head>
               <p>VSe the ſame practiſe as is ſhewed before for the Spauan. Or, Burne the Soraunce in the myddes and ouerthwarte, after this fourme folowynge. <figure/> Fower howres after take Cowes dunge newe made, and Salade oyle myxte and well beaten together: and there with annnoynte the foreſayde places. But note this, that you ſhall hardly cure the Spauan or Splent, but at theyr beginninge. Or, Slitte the Soraunce al the length of it and let it bleede: and when it hath left bleeding, caſte the horſe, and keepe him downe in ſuche ſorte that he maie not ſtyre, and powre into the place that is ſlytte Boares greaſe made ſcaldynge hotte.
<pb facs="tcp:3085:7"/>
But firſt make about the ſlitte a coffin with claie, to kepe in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayde greaſe vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſayde ſlytte, and ſo let it reſt, vntill it be colde, then let the horſe ryſe and with one dreſſyng it will ridde y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Sora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unce cleane awaye, without any eye ſore or ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſhe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="part">
               <head>15 The Curbe.</head>
               <p>YOu may vſe the practyſe before for the ſpaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or ſplent. Or ſlytte the Curbe all the length, then take a piece of lynnen cloth, and weat it in wyne made hotte, and ſtrowe therupon Verd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>degriſe hot vpon the ſaid ſlit, and binde it ſo that it fal not away.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="part">
               <head>16 The Crepanchies.</head>
               <p>TAke a qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>titie of vnſleked lyme, halfe ſo much of blacke ſope, and ſo muche of ſtronge vyne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger as ſhall ſuffice, make therof an oynctme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, and annoynte the place withall, and let not the ſayde oynctment be rubbed of, vntill a daie or two be paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and it will deſtroye and kill the Soraunce: the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> waſhe the place once or twiſe with warme wyne, after that heale it as you doe other wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des. Kepe the place cleane from filth and myre.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="part">
               <head>17 The Paennes or Paynes.</head>
               <p>VSe the foreſaid practiſe ſhewed for the Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panchies. Or, Take Peper, Garlyke, Cole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woortes, and olde Barrowes greaſe, make a playſter therof, and lay it to the Soraunce, and within a fewe daies, it will heale it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:3085:7"/>
               <head>18 The ſwellynge of the Coddes.</head>
               <p>TAke Beane flower, wheate meale, cummyne, and Barrowes greaſe make a plaiſter there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of and ſpreade it all ouer the roddes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="part">
               <head>19 Cloyed or prycked.</head>
               <p>PAre the hoofe to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> quicke where the hurte is, and lay to that place flare or hardes dieped in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> white of an egge: after that ſtuffe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hole with ſalte beate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſmal, mingled with Veruin and ſtrong vineger, and couer it with flaxe or hardes diped in very ſtrong vineger. If a ſtubbe, nayle, or any other ſuch lyke thinge be runne into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> foote, pull it out: then holde vp his foote, and powre in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de hote ſcaldynge oyle Olyfe, and whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that is colde, powre into it hotte Terebe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tyne, and that beynge colde, ſtrowe vpon it the powlder of Sulphur, lay therupo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a bolſter of flaxe, then ſhooe him, and keepe his foote from myre and water. And for all hurtes of the foote. Take tallowe, the poulder of Sulphur, Mallowes, and very ſtronge vyneger, boyle the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> together vntyll they be thicke, lyke vnto an oynctme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t: lay the ſame to the foote, as hotte as he canne endure it, and ſo lette it reſt xii. howres. If y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> foote feſtureth by euyll curing, or for wante of lookynge to it in due time, then pare the hoofe vnder the foote vnto the quick, and vſe the practiſe before preſcribed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:3085:8"/>
               <head>25 Enterferynge, hewynge, or breakynge.</head>
               <p>SOmetyme it co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth of weakenes, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> remedie therof is, to feede thy horſe wel: if it co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth of any other cauſe, the rounde paringe of his hoofe, and the well ſhooynge ſhall helpe that faulte muche.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="part">
               <head>21 Shouldred.</head>
               <p>IF thy horſe by any happe be wrinched on the ſhoulder, rowel him on the place that is gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued croſſe wiſe, the one ouerthwarte the other walke him euenynge and moringe ſoftely, that the humours may flow thither and iſſue foorth, and thruſt out the ſame humours often tymes in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> daie with thy handes or ſkotch the place with an hot y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron all the length of the ſhoulder, and ouertwhart in ſuch ſorte that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcotches maye be comely, and no diſfyguringe to the place: vſe the ſame practiſe for euery wrinche or ſwellynge.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="part">
               <head>* Broken legge. 22.</head>
               <p>FIrſt bringe the bones into their right places: then wrappe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> about with vnwaſhed woulle pulled fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſheepes backe, and rolle it with rol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les of lynne<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> colth dieped in oyle and vyneger, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſple<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te it with ſplentes on thre of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſydes, and binde the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dſomely, and let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſtill ſo .xl. daies, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe by occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou ſhalt be enforced to chaunge y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> rollers, to new bynde the fore ſaid ſplents: but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies
<pb facs="tcp:3085:8"/>
kepe the place moiſt with vyneger &amp; ſalet oyle: after .xl. daies (if the bones be growen well together) remoue all the foreſayd thinges, and an<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>noint dailye the place with ſome ſewet. And note this, that all bones broken aboue the kenee, be for the moſt part vncurable.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="part">
               <head>* The Scabbe, or Maunge. 23</head>
               <p>IF it commeth of abundaunce of bludde or hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours, then lette him blud on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> necke veine, and cowell him vnder y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> necke that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> humurs may iſſue forth: then rubbe his bodie all ouer with an harde heare cloth, or corrie combe, vntil it blee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, after that annoynt his bodie with this oin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctement. Take Sulphur, ſalte, and Tartar, of eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one of them lyke quantitie, beate the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per them with very ſtronge vyneger, and the lyke quantitie of oyle, and therwith annoint him.</p>
               <p>Or take very ſtronge vyneger, the vrine of a bore vnder .xii. yeres of age, and the iuyce of Humlocks mixe them together and waſh thy horſe therwith</p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="part">
               <head>24 The Fiſtula, or the Pole yuell.</head>
               <p>TAke vnſleked lyme, and Arſenike of eche lyke quantitie, beate them together into verye fyne poulder, put thereto the iuyce of garlike, oynio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, and walwoorte, or Dane woorte, of lyke quanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and honye, ſo muche as the iuyce of the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayde three, boyle them on a ſofte fyre, and ſtyre them well together vntyll they bee as thycke
<pb facs="tcp:3085:9"/>
as an oynctment: then waſhe the Soraunce with very ſtronge vyneger, and fill the hole ful of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fore ſayde oynctment twiſe in the daie, and binde ſome<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thing about the mouth of it, that the ſayde oynct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment maie not runne out. Or, Take Orpiment, vnſleked lyme, Verdegryſe, of each lyke quantitie tpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>er the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with the iuyce of Paretarie, blake inke, hony, and ſtronge vyneger, of lyke quantitie, boyle them, and ſtirre them well together vntil they be very thicke: the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> make therof rolles (as it were ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitories) and put them into the holow place of the ſaid Soraunce. Note that thou ſhalt neuer he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ale a Fiſtula or Canker, vntill thou ſhalt haue kil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led it at the bottome: when it is kylled, healle it, ſtrowe on it or put into it the poulder of Sauyn, or the poulder of hony and vnſleked lyme burnte together, or Tarre and oyle myxte together.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="part">
               <head>25 The Farcyn.</head>
               <p>LEt him bludde at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beginninge of his diſeaſe, but in no wyſe in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> myddes thereof: the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> burne thoſe places where y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhalt eſpie any ſwellyng or Farcyn to appere. (Note: that it is muche better to burn an horſe with copper the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with yro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes) then heale the foreſayde burninges with Tarre, Oyle, and Honie mixte together: and geue him with Malmeſey y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> poulder of <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>apente</hi> hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ende ſhewed. Or, geue him fowre ou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces of the poulder of Walwoorte or Danewoorte, with a pinte &amp; an halfe of good wine thre daies together.
<pb facs="tcp:3085:9"/>
After that take halfe an ounce of Aloes, one ou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of Centaure, one ounce of <hi>Opoponax,</hi> beate them al into fyne poulder, and geue them him to drinke in a pinte and an halfe of wyne warmed, wherin the rootes of the foreſayd hearbe called walwoorte, or Danewoorte haue bene boyled. Vſe to ryde him ofte vntill he be all on a ſweate. And when he is cured put him to paſture, for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> running in paſture in the open ayre is very good.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="part">
               <head>26 The Canker.</head>
               <p>TAke Sauyn, Bay ſalte, and Rue, ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pe them together with Barrowes greaſe and lay this oynctment to it vntill it be killed, whiche thou ſhalt knowe by the whytenes: then heale it, as is before preſcribed for the Fiſtula.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="part">
               <head>27 The Feſture or Tetre.</head>
               <p>TAke a ſnake, cutte of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> head and tayle, thro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we them away, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reſt cutte in to ſmal pieces, roſte them on a ſpitte, take y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> greaſe that drop<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>peth from them, in ſtill the ſame hotte vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the So<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, &amp; it wil heale it wunderfully in very ſhorte tyme, but touche none other parte with the fore<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſaid oynetment but onely the Soraunce.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="part">
               <head>28 An Vlcere.</head>
               <p>TAke Copperas and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> leaues of Lillies, beate them well together in a morter with ſwynes
<pb facs="tcp:3085:10"/>
greaſe, therwith annoynt the ſore and it wil heale it. Oyle Olife inſtilled hotte vpon it, or the poul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of Galles ſtrowed vpon it, is very good.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="29" type="part">
               <head>29 An inpoſtume or mattrie ſore.</head>
               <p>FIrſt when it is ripe launce it vnder the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce after the fygure of a newe moone, as thus, <g ref="char:Moonnew">●</g> for that maner of inciſion is beſt to cauſe the matter to iſſue forth: then waſhe it with warme vryne, after that annoynt it with tarre and oyle myxt together. Note that the launcing of it with an hotte yron, is better, then with a colde knife.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="30" type="part">
               <head>* Woundes. 30</head>
               <p>TO heale woundes, Take .viii. dra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mes of Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rebe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tine, fowre dra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mes of new virgin ware, melte the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in anewe pewter veſſell, ſtirre the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> well together, and when that they be well molte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> take the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from the fyre, and by and by whiles they be hot, powre into the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> half a pinte of good whyte wyne, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> after they be colde throw away y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wine, and annoynte thy ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des with oyle of Roſes, and, woorke the ware and Terebentine well together. After that put the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> into the pewter veſſell againe, then put to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> halfe an ounce of the gu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me of firre tree, and three dra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mes of the iuyce of betony, ſeath the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> together vntil the iuyce of Betonie be waſted, then put to it .iiii. dra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mes of woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s milke, or the milke of a redde cowe, and ſeath them once agyne
<pb facs="tcp:3085:10"/>
vntill the mylke be waſted, and ſo kepe it for it is very good. Or, Take Roſemary, and drie it in the ſhadowe, beate it into fyne poulder, waſhe the wound with vyneger, or the vryne of a chylde, and ſtrowe theron the foreſayde poulder: or the poulder of hony and vnſleked lyme burnt together.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="30" type="part">
               <head>* Woundes or ſore. 30.</head>
               <p>TAke wormewoode, Mayoram, Pimpernel, Calamynt dried, <hi>Olibanum,</hi> beate them all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to finepouldre, then take waxe and barrowes greaſe and boyle them on a ſofte fyte vntyll they be as thicke as an ointment or ſalue, make a plai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter therof and laye it vpon the ſoraunces.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="31" type="part">
               <head>* To drawe out a ſtubbe, thorne, or iron out of the fleſhe. 31.</head>
               <p>TAke reede rootes, ſtampe them with hony, or take ſnayles without ſhelles, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly called ſlugges, ſlampe them together with butter, frie them and laye them to the pla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, and thei will drawe out the thorne, ſtubbe, or iron. When the thorne, ſtubbe, or iron, is come fourth, laye vpon the wounde the whyte of an egge, by the ſpace of xii. houres, and after that, heale it as it is ſhewed before for woundes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="32" type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:3085:11"/>
               <head>* Ache, payne, or ſwellynge in the ſinewes. 32.</head>
               <p>TAke the flower of Lyne ſeede, Terebentine, and honie, of eache like qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>titie, boyle them w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> white wine vntil they be thick like vnto an oynctment, lay them vpon the griefe, and ſpreade thereon a peece of cloth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="33" type="part">
               <head>* Shorte wynded. 33.</head>
               <p>TAke Nutmigges, Cloues, Gala<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gale, Carda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>momu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or Graines of Paradiſe, of euerie of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> three dra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mes, Carraway ſeede, and Feni<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>greke ſomewhat more in quantitie the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the foure a foreſayde, a like quantitie of Saffro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and halfe an ounce of Liquorize, beate them all into very fyne poulder, put vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a pynte of good whyte wine, and the yolkes of fower egges, beate them all well together, &amp; then geue them to thy horſe to drynke: let him ſtande with his heade hanged vp high one whole howre, that he may not caſt out y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> foreſaide drinke: after that, eyther walke him, or ryde him ſoftely, but let him not eate or drinke all that daie after, nor the night before, to thinte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayde drinke maye the better woorke on him: and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> nexte daie put him to paſture, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> coldneſſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gras may ſomewhat abate y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> heate of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> foreſaid drinke. Or, Take <hi>Capill<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s Veneris, Ireos,</hi> Aſhe keyes, Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quorize, Fenigreke, and Reiſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, of eueri of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> one
<pb facs="tcp:3085:11"/>
dramme and an halfe: graynes of Paradiſe Peper ſower Almons, Baurach, Nettle ſeede, ariſtol o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chia, and Coloquintida, of euery one two dra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mes, Algaricum one dramme and an halfe, honi two .li. diſſolue them with water wherein Liquorize is ſodde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and geue him to drinke therof thre or fowre tymes, and it wil helpe him, if that the diſeaſe hath not longe continued vpon him.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="34" type="part">
               <head>* The Cough. 34</head>
               <p>TAke the whytes and yolkes of two egges, three ounces of oyle Olyfe, two ſponeful of Beane flower, one ounce of Fenigreke, one ſponeful of the pouder of Enula campana, mingle all theſe together in a pinte of good Malmeſey, and geue it him to drinke three daies together. Or, Take Tarre, and Barrowes greaſe, or freſhe but<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, mingle them together and geue therof to thy horſe .iiii. tymes in .vii. daies: that is, the friſt daie, the thirde daie, the fyfth daie, and the ſeue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>th daie.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="35" type="part">
               <head>* The Bottes. 35</head>
               <p>TAke the bowelles of ayounge pullet, and geue them to thy horſe to ſwallowe downe warme, and let him neyther eate nor drinke in fowre how<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>res after. Or, geue him the croppes of Sother<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nwood to eate with his prouender. Or, geue him woorme ſeede, or brimſtone, or the pouder of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uin to drinke with ale, beere, or Malmeſey.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="36" type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:3085:12"/>
               <head>* The frettynge of the beally. 36</head>
               <p>ANnoynt thy hande with Salade oyle, butter: or greaſe, and thruſte it in at his fundament, put out the harde dunge that letteth the paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge of the excrementes: after that, with ſome clyſter pipe conueigh into his intrailes water and ſalte mixt together. Or make a ſuppoſitorie of honie and a quantitie of ſalte, of good le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth, and as byg as an heunes egge, and put it in at his fundame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. Geue him to drinke the poulder of Centaury or woormewood with malmeſey.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="37" type="part">
               <head>* The Squynte or Fulre. 37</head>
               <p>KEpe him from labour: let him drinke very ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and that very little and warme, min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled with wheate meale: and burne him with an hot yron about the nauyll: the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> geue him to drinke a pinte of redde wyne, with the poulder of a Nut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>migge, halfe an ounce of Synamone, and as mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che of the rinde of a Pomegranate.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="38" type="part">
               <head>* Lunge ſicke. 38</head>
               <p>TAke the bludde of a yonge ſuckynge pygge, and geue it thy horſe to drinke whiles it is warme. After that take one headde of Garlyke, bray it, and mingle it with butter, or Barrowes greaſe, make balles thereof &amp; geue them to thy horſe to ſwalow downe: then take halfe a pinte of malmeſey, fowre newe layed egges, and three ou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces of honie, mingle
<pb facs="tcp:3085:12"/>
them together, and geue it him to drinke three da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ies together.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="39" type="part">
               <head>* The Yalowes. A diſeaſe of the harte, and to be diſcerned by the eyes. 39</head>
               <p>FIrſte pull out with thy ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de the harde clottered dunge (as is before preſcribed for the frettyng of the bealy) tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> geue him a ſuppoſitorie, made with ſalte, hony, and maiorame, as is there alſo ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed. Let him bludde in the necke veyne, and ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unche not the bleedynge vntill thou ſhalt ſee the bludde pure &amp; good. Then geue him to drinke three ounces of Myrre beaten into fine poulder, with a pinte of good malmeſey. Some vſe to take y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> iuyce of yuie leaues mingled with wine, and ſquirte it warme into his noſethrilles. Let his drinke be colde water mixed with Vitrum, and feede him with graſſe or newe hay, ſprinkled with water and Vitrum mingled together.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>* Languiſhe.</head>
               <p>TAke halfe a pinte of good malmeſey, &amp; as mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che of the bludde of a yonge ſucking pigge, geue it him warme to drinke. Or, geue him malmeſey with the iuyce of Feuerfew. Or, take an ounce of Sulphur viue beaten into fyne poulder, the wei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ght of one peny of the poulder, of Myrre, beate them well together with a newe laide egge, and geue them to drinke with halfe a pinte of good malmeſey: vſe it for it is very good.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>* To prouoke an horſe to ſtale.</head>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:3085:13"/>TAke fyue lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge oynions the ſharpeſt that thou canſt gette, or garlike: bruiſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and thruſt them in at his fundament ſo farre as thou canſt, and put ſome therof into his yarde: after that ryde him, or gallop him. Or, take the grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des or the cleye of horſe vrine, mingle it with white wyne, and ſquirt it in at his noſethrilles.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="42" type="part">
               <head>* To make Diapence. 42</head>
               <p>TAke <hi>Gentum, Ariſtol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>chia,</hi> Mirre, Bayberies, &amp; the ſhauinges of Elephantes tooth of euery one like quantitie, beate all together in fine poulder, and geue a ſpoonefull of the ſaid poulder in a pinte and an halfe of good malmeſey. It hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth and preſerueth from al inwarde maladies and infections. Therfore beneuer without the foreſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de poulder, and aſſone as thou ſhalt eſpy thy horſe drooping or droowſy, geue him thereof as is afo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſayde, and thou ſhalt fynde the vertue therof.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="43" type="part">
               <head>* The poulder of hony and lyme. 43</head>
               <p>Take ſuche a quantitie of vnſleked lyme as thou ſhalt thinke beſt, beate it into fyne poul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der, then take ſo much hony as ſhal ſuffice, mingle the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> together, a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d make as it were ſtife paſte of them in the forme of a thicke cake or lofe, then put the ſame cake or lofe into a hot burnyng fyre, and burne it there vntill it be glowing redde and through burnte, take it forth, when it is colde beate it into fyne poulder and vſe it: it dreth, healeth, and ſkynneth meruaylouſly wel</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:3085:13"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3085:14"/>
            <trailer>END</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
